<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % local.common.attrib "xmlns:xi  CDATA  #FIXED 'http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude'">
]>
<section id="gtu-Considerations">
  <sectioninfo>
    <title role="top_of_page" id="gtu-Considerations.top_of_page">Important Considerations</title>
    <sectpurpose>Gotchas to look out for</sectpurpose>
  </sectioninfo>

  <toc></toc>

  <section>
    <title>Interoperation with the GLib test framework</title>
    <para>
      To minimise the amount of code (and the opportunity for bugs), GTU
      depends on GLib test APIs for providing certain functionality. However,
      we also rewrite functionality or hack around GLib's implementation when
      it isn't sufficiently flexible for our purposes. The end result is that
      much of GLib's test API cannot be used alongside GTU.
    </para>

    <para>
      This is a list of GLib test functions that should work as normal:
    </para>

    <xi:include href="gfuncs-okay.xml"/>

    <para>
      The following is a (possibly incomplete) list of GLib functionality that
      will provoke undefined behaviour if used in tandem with GTU:
    </para>

    <xi:include href="gfuncs-avoid.xml"/>

    <para>
      Additionally, test suites using GTU are incompatible with GLib's
      <command>gtester</command> utility.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Logging</title>
    <para>
      Test suites/cases should be careful not to write arbitrary data to
      <varname>stdout</varname>, as this is the mechanism by which GTU
      communicates with the test harness. Whilst writing to
      <varname>stderr</varname> should be safe (as per the
      <ulink url="http://testanything.org/tap-specification.html">TAP specification</ulink>),
      it's recommended that this is avoided for the sake of test log legibility
      and (potentially) compatibility with buggy test harnesses.
    </para>

    <para>
      Test cases wishing to log additional information should do so via
      <link linkend="g-message"><function>g_message()</function></link> or
      <link linkend="g-log"><function>g_log()</function></link>; GTU installs
      default log handlers to emit messages to the test log correctly. Using
      the structured logging API is currently unsupported.  Test suites should
      avoid installing their own default log handlers.
    </para>

    <para>
      Test case writers are encouraged (but not required) to consider whether
      some logged information is essential to the test log. Most test case
      output can likely be hidden behind a check for
      <link linkend="GTU-TEST-MODE-FLAGS-VERBOSE:CAPS"><constant>GTU_TEST_MODE_FLAGS_VERBOSE</constant></link>.
      No such consideration is required for
      <link linkend="GTU-TEST-MODE-FLAGS-QUIET:CAPS"><constant>GTU_TEST_MODE_FLAGS_QUIET</constant></link>,
      as this is handled automatically by GTU.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
